Guide to the Molly Neuman Riot Grrrl Collection, 1986-2002 (Bulk 1988-1996) MSS.289
Fales Library and Special Collections
Molly Neuman Riot Grrrl Collection
1986-2002
1988-1996
Fales Library and Special Collections
Neuman, Molly
MSS.289
9 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 2 flat boxes, and 1 oversize flat box.
Molly Neuman is a musician, writer, and artist who was active in the Riot Grrrl movement from its inception. The Molly Neuman Riot Grrrl Collection contain correspondence, zines, photography, and documentation pertaining to Molly Neuman, her connections with the Riot Grrrl movement, and her involvement with the band Bratmobile.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
The collection remains in original order for the most part, except in the case of Series II and III, where some materials where placed into chronological order as appropriate.
A majority of the photographs were collected into albums by Molly Neuman and their original order has not been altered.
Biographical Note
Molly Neuman is a musician, writer, and chef who was active in the Riot Grrrl movement from its inception. The term "riot grrrl" was first coined in a zine co-written by Neuman and her friend Alison Wolfe while the two were studying at University of Oregon. Their collaboration on this zine--called "Girl Germs"--lead Neuman and Wolfe to form Bratmobile, a feminist, punk-influenced band, with Erin Smith. Both Neuman and Wolfe eventually transferred to Evergreen College in Olympia, Washington where they become more involved with the Riot Grrrl movement.
Bratmobile was primarily active from 1991-1994, releasing two albums on the record label Kill Rock Stars and releasing songs on various other compilations/split 7" records during that period. After the band disbanded, Neuman went on to be a part of several other bands including the Frumpies and the PeeChees, the latter of which featured her ex-husband Chris Appelgren. Bratmobile reunited briefly in 1999, eventually touring with the Donnas in 2001, whom Neuman was managing at the time. Bratmobile released two albums after reforming, 2000's "Ladies, Women and Girls" and 2002's "Girls Get Busy".
Neuman was a partner with Appelgren at Lookout Records, a label which produced albums by acts including Green Day, Avail, and Pansy Division. In 2005, Lookout discontinued releasing new projects and Neuman began her own small label, Simple Social Graces Discos, releasing several records including the Delorean, the Two Tears and her own band, Love or Perish. In 2006, she joined the team at eMusic and continues to work there as Senior Director of Artist and Label relations.
In 2009, she graduated from the Chef's Training Program at New Yorks Natural Gourmet Institute. Following graduation, Neuman opened Simple Social Kitchen, a personal chef, catering and culinary instruction company based in Brooklyn, NY. She is currently working on a program aimed at creative people and health in the effort to connect all her passions.
Sources:
www.killrockstars.com www.eastbayexpress.com www.allmusic.com www.simplesocialkitchen.com
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be accessible to researchers.
Scope and Content
The Molly Neuman Riot Grrrl Collection contains materials pertaining to Neuman's life between 1986-2002 (bulk 1988-1996). A majority of the collection is comprised of personal correspondence and journals that document Molly's participation in the Riot Grrrl movement, her experiences in various bands including Bratmobile, and her creative output as a filmmaker, photographer, and writer. Some materials pertaining to Neuman's later involvement with Lookout! Records and her management of The Donnas are also included. Items in the collection range from 1986-2002, with the bulk from 1988-1996.
The collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Correspondence contains personal correspondence received by Molly Neuman between 1986and 2002, including fan mail for Bratmobile and zine submissions.
Subseries A: Alphabetically Filed Correspondence
Subseries B: Miscellaneous Unfiled Correspondence
Series II: Zines, Notebooks, and Papers contains original zines, Molly's personal notebooks/diaries, press clippings pertaining to her musical career, and uncategorized papers collected in the course of her studies and travels.
Subseries A: Zines and Zine-related
Subseries B: Notebooks
Subseries C: Miscellaneous Papers and Documentation
Series III: Photography contains photographs of Bratmobile, creative and academic work by Molly Neuman, and other visual artifacts.
Subseries A: Loose Photos and Negatives
Subseries B: Photos, Slides, and Negatives in Binders [as arranged by Neuman]
Series IV: Realia contains t-shirts created as merchandise for the PeeChees, a band Molly Neuman was in from 1994-1998.
Subseries A: T-shirts
Series V: Media contains film created by Molly Neuman, as well as video and audio items owned or made by Molly.
Subseries A: Film
Subseries B: Audio and Video
Zines; Photography |z United States.; Feminism; Correspondence.; Slides (photographs); Riot grrrl movement.; Punk culture.; Film.; Rock music -- United States -- 1991-2000; Hanna, Kathleen, 1968-; Neuman, Molly; Wolfe, Allison; Smith, Erin; Bratmobile (Musical group)
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Content
  Series I: Correspondence contains personal correspondence received by Molly Neuman between 1986and 2002, including fan mail for Bratmobile and zine submissions.
  - Subseries A: Alphabetically Filed Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under A, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under B [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under B [2 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under B & "Brat Correspondence", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under C, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under D, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under E, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under F, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under G, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under H [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under H [2 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under I-J [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under I-J [2 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under K, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under L [1 of 3], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under L [2 of 3], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under L [3 of 3], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under M, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under N [1 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under N [2 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under N [3 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under O, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under P-Q, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under R, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under S [1 of 4], undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under S [2 of 4], undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under S [3 of 4], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under S [4 of 4], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under T [1 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under T [2 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under U-V, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under W, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: Filed Under X-Y-Z, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Subseries B: Miscellaneous Unfiled Correspondence
    - Uncategorized Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series II: Zines, Notebooks, and Papers
  Series II: Zines, Notebooks, and Papers contains original zines, Molly's personal notebooks/diaries, press clippings pertaining to her musical career, and uncategorized papers collected in the course of her studies and travels.
  - Subseries A: Zines and Zine-related
    - Riot Grrrl Zine, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Riot Grrrl No. 4, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Girl Germs No. 3, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Abstract
      Olympia-based Bratmobile members Molly Neuman and Allison Wolfe begin this issue of their riot grrrl zine with reminiscence on female solidarity and letters from readers. Contributions include an extended piece on the Asian experience in the United States and resulting struggles to maintain ethnic identity in the face of discrimination. Other themes include lesbian relations, violence against women, and sexual abuse. Further elements include a column debunking masturbation myths, serialized fiction, an extended top ten list, reviews of video artist Sadie Benning and new music, an interview with Rebecca of Love Child, and a list of zines. Concludes with a narrative describing the origins of Girl Germs.
    - "Girl Germs" file, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Notebooks
    - Notebook 1, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Notebook 2, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notebook 3, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notebook 4, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Notebook 5, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notebook 6, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Notebook 7, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Notebook 8, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Notebook 9, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Notebook 10, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notebook 11, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Notebook 12, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Notebook 13, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Notebook 14, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Notebook 15, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Notebook 16, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Notebook 17, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Notebook 18, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Notebook 19, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notebook 20, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notebook 21, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Notebook 22, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notebook 23, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Journal 2 Fall 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Travel Diary, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Address Book 1, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Address Book 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Wallet Contents, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Filofax Contents, 1993-1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Subseries C: Miscellaneous Papers and Documentation
    - Bratmobile, Molly Neuman, and Misc. Press Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Binder Contents--Filmmaking & Photography & Misc Papers, 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 1, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 2, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 3, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 4, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series III: Photography
  Contains photographs of Bratmobile, creative and academic work by Molly Neuman, and other visual artifacts. A majority of the photographs were collected into albums by Molly Neuman and their original order has not been altered.
  - Subseries A: Loose Photos and Negatives
    - Miscellaneous Photos [1 of 2], undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Photos [2 of 2], undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Subseries B: Photos, Slides, and Negatives in Binders
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #1, undated; slides (Box 4)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #2, undated; photos and negatives (Box 4)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #3, undated; photos and negatives (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #4, undated; photos and negatives (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #5, undated; photos and negatives (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #6, undated; photos (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #7, undated; photos (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #8, undated; photos (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #9, undated; photos (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #10, undated; photos (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #11, undated; photos (Box 5)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #12, undated; photos (Box 6)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #13, undated; photos (Box 6)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #14, undated; photos (Box 6)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #15, undated; photos (Box 6)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #16, undated; photos (Box 6)
    - Molly Neuman: Binder #17, undated; photos (Box 6)
- Series IV: Realia
  Contains t-shirts created as merchandise for the PeeChees, a band Molly Neuman was in from 1994-1998.
  - Subseries A: T-shirts
    - PeeChees t-shirts, undated; three t-shirts (Box 7, Object data_value_missing_83f4180f00e9280bb82f2b72db419a2e)
- Series V: Media
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - Subseries A: Film, 12 reels of motion picture film (mixed formats) (Box 9)
  - Subseries B: Audio and Video
    - [Schroeder 12345 Original] VHS tape, undated (Box 8, Media ID: 289.0001)
    - [Sweetness, I was Only Joking] VHS Tape, undated (Box 8, Media ID: 289.0002)
    - [For Molly Germs] Audio Cassette Tape, undated (Box 8, Media ID: 289.0003)
    - [Are You Only Gonna Interview Boys?] [Gary W Lemans Birthday] Audio Cassette Tape, 1-5-1992 (Box 8, Media ID: 289.0004)
    - [Helter Skillex] [Be Mine] Audio Cassette Tape, undated (Box 8, Media ID: 289.0005)
    - Pork "Squeal" 7" vinyl record (Box 8, Media ID: 289.0006)